<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "./reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ogud-dnsop-any-notimp"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="1035">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes"?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Refusing ANY query">
      Standard way for Authoratitive DNS servers to refuse ANY query </title>
     
      <author fullname="Olafur Gudmundsson" initials="O." surname="Gudmundsson">
	<organization>CloudFlare Inc.</organization>
	<address>
	  <postal>
	    <street></street>
	    <city>San Francisco</city>
	    <region>CA</region>
	    <code>94107</code>
	    <country>USA</country>
	  </postal>
	  <email>olafur@cloudflare.com</email>
	</address>
      </author>

      <author fullname="Marek Majkowski" initials="M." surname="Majkowski">
	<organization>CloudFlare Inc.</organization>
	<address>
	  <postal>
	    <street></street>
	    <city>London</city>
	    <region></region>
	    <code></code>
	    <country>UK</country>
	  </postal>
	  <email>marek@cloudflare.com</email>
	</address>
      </author>

      <date />
      
      <area>Operations</area>
      
      <workgroup>DNSOP</workgroup>
      
      <abstract>
	<t> DNS ANY query is widely abused for reflection attacks. This
	feature was designed to aid in debugging. As there is no good
	reason for applications to ever issue an ANY query this
	document codifies how an authoritative server can reject such
	queries. 
	  </t> 
      </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
  <section title="Introduction"> 
    <t> DNS is an evolving protocol, at glacial phase, this document
    specifies how an Authorative server can reject an ANY query. ANY
    queries are widely abused by attackers doing reflection attacks as
    they return the largest answers. Over the years a number of attempts have been
    made to throttle ANY queries, ranging from returning TC bit to all
    UDP ANY queries, blocking them totally, and QoS'ing the number of
    ANY queires accepted per second. All of those are band-aids. 
    </t> 
    <t> 
      Some modern Authoritative servers, such as those used by CDN's,
      do not have DNS zones. For those servers answering ANY query
      truthfully is hard work. Thus ignoring ANY queries simplifies
      the implementation.
    </t> 
    </section>
    <section title="Requirements notation">
      <t>
	The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
	this document are to be interpreted as described in
	<xref target="RFC2119" />.
      </t>
    </section> 

    <section title="Protocol change"> 
      <t> 
	An Authorative DNS<xref target="RFC1035" /> server can reject ANY query by returning
	RCODE = 4 (NOTIMP). 
      </t> 
      <t> 
	A Recurisive Resolver SHOULD ignore RD bit set on ANY
	query. Additionaly as Recursive Resolver SHOULD remember that
	ANY queries are not available from upstream Auth server, this
	SHOULD be cached for at least 5 minutes.
      </t> 
    </section> 
  
  <section title="IANA considerations">
      <t> No IANA action is requested </t> 
  </section>

  <section title="Security considerations"> 
    <t> ANY query is mainly used for attacks on the internet due to
      its amplification factor. Codifying this behavior makes life
      harder for attackers, at minimal cost for DNS operators.
    </t> 
  </section>

  <section title="Internationalizaiton Considerations"> 
    <t> NONE</t>
  </section> 

  <section title="Implementation Experience"> 
    <t> TBD
    </t>
  </section> 
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1035'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
    </references>
    
    <section title="Document history"> 
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>
      <t> 00 Initial version </t> 
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
